Finding Aid for M.O.S.E.S., Records, 1993-2003 (bulk dates, 1998-2001)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
M.O.S.E.S., Records 1993-2003, 1998-2001
M.O.S.E.S.
3 linear feet
048 Ba 2
Inter-racial, inter-faith organization established in 1997 to strengthen metropolitan Detroit congregations and communities through social programs, leadership training, and encouragement of civic participation. M.O.S.E.S was formed from three faith-based organizations: Jeremiah, West Detroit Inter-faith Community Organization, and NOAH. The name M.O.S.E.S. is an acronym for Metropolitan Organizing Strategy Enabling Strength
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was deposited by the organization in September 2003 (donor no. 9383 ).
The collection is open to research.
M.O.S.E.S., Metropolitan Organizing Strategy Enabling Strength, is an inter-racial, inter-faith community organization in Southeast Michigan. It was founded in 1997, by the leaders of three faith-based organizations in Detroit, Michigan: Jeremiah, West Detroit Inter-Faith Community Organization (WDIFCO-RUTH), and NOAH. Its main purpose is to strengthen the congregations and communities of metropolitan Detroit through social programs, leadership training, and participating in the public arena and democracy to cause beneficial change.
M.O.S.E.S. is concerned with any issues facing the residents of the metropolitan area. They work to fight urban sprawl and improve the area communities. Some of their most concentrated efforts have been supporting public transportation, crime and public safety issues, and sponsoring youth programs. M.O.S.E.S. has successfully petitioned the Michigan state government for money to support public transportation, obtaining state money in 2000 and helping pass the Regional Transit Authority bill in 2002. They have also started a campaign, “Fix it First,” to encourage the Michigan state legislature to allocate funds towards improving existing roads before funding new road projects.
A major achievement of M.O.S.E.S. was the establishment of “safe zones” around the area churches in 1996. They worked with local law officials to clean up the neighborhoods, combat drugs, and increase police presence. They have continued their efforts by obtaining additional funds for drug enforcement, building new houses, and maintaining their relationship with the police and civic officials.
M.O.S.E.S. is active in Wayne, Oakland, and Macomb counties, and is divided into three districts (JEREMIAH, RUTH, and NOAH). M.O.S.E.S. coordinates the districts and is responsible for obtaining funding, setting budgets, and providing training to district leaders. Each district is responsible for local recruitment, overseeing local staff, and developing projects for that area. By dividing M.O.S.E.S. into districts, they kept the number of congregations in each group small enough to be able to interact efficiently. M.O.S.E.S. is funded by dues from each member congregation and through an annual fund-raiser. The year’s activities are divided into trimesters: core team development, public action, and fund raising. Each trimester involves all members of M.O.S.E.S., begins with training, and ends with a major event.
More current information is available at the M.O.S.E.S. website, http://www.mosesmi.org/
The M.O.S.E.S. records are divided into four series: History and Activities, Financial, Jeremiah Project Board, and M.O.S.E.S. Executive Board.
Subjects:
M.O.S.E.S.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Environmental justice--Michigan.; Jeremiah Project (Detroit, Mich.); Housing policy--Michigan--Religious aspects.; Transportation and state--Michigan--Religious aspects.; West Detroit Inter-faith Community Organization.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
M.O.S.E.S.; Jeremiah Project (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- History and Activities
  The History and Activities series covers the creation and structure of M.O.S.E.S., and its missions and bylaws. Daily activities are recorded through the Weekly Reports, written by the M.O.S.E.S. director Bill O’Brien from October 1997 - January 2002, photocopied newspaper articles pertaining to M.O.S.E.S. projects and predecessor organizations from February 1994 - September 2001, and records of the planning and evaluation of programs.
  - History, Bylaws, and Organizational Structure (Box 1)
  - Weekly Reports October 1997-January 2002 (Box 1)
  - Planning and Evaluation 2000-2002, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - News Letters and Pamphlets 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Press Clippings 1994-2001, 2003, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (includes material on predecessors of M.O.S.E.S.)
  - Declaration of Interdependence 1998 (Box 1)
  - Videos
    - Jeremiah Project (Box 1)
    - M.O.S.E.S. (Box 1)
    - Waterfall Safe Zone 1997 (Box 1)
    - Together for a Change (Box 1)
- Financial
  The Financial series is comprised of two subseries: grant applications and budget. Grant applications consists of the applications for several grants, and correspondence related to each grant. Applications were made from 1995-2001 and include the first grants to form the metropolitan-wide cooperation that would become M.O.S.E.S. Budget includes budget information for 1999 and 2001, records of the financial committee from 1999-2001, and audits of M.O.S.E.S. in 1997 and WDIFCO (a predecessor of M.O.S.E.S.) in 1996 and 1997.
  - Grant Applications
    - Campaign for Human Development (National), to fund the Metro Organizing Strategy 1995-1996, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Hudson Webber Foundation, for Safe Zone Project 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - M.O.S.E.S. Coalition on Recreation Centered Drug Prevention concept paper 1997 (Box 1)
    - Beldon Fund, for land use and sprawl issues 2000 (Box 1)
    - Campaign for Human Development (Local), Jeremiah Project 2000 (Box 1)
    - Campaign for Human Development (Local), M.O.S.E.S. 2000 (Box 1)
    - Charles Stewart Mott Foundation, Michigan Transportation Policy and Growth Management 2000 (Box 1)
    - Community Foundation for SE Michigan, for the Safe Zone Project 2000 (Box 1)
    - Dominican Sisters of Illinois Poverty, Justice, and Peace Fund 2001 (Box 1)
  - Budget
    - Budget 1999, 2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Financial Committee 1999, 2000, 2001, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - M.O.S.E.S. Audited Financial Statements for 1997 (Box 1)
    - WDIFCO Audit for 1996, 1997 (Box 1)
      (predecessor of M.O.S.E.S.)
- Jeremiah Project Board
  The Jeremiah Project Board series contains five binders, covering the years 1993-1999. The information includes board and executive board meeting agendas and minutes, financial reports, and goal statements, as well as the materials given to members to prepare for each meeting. There is also a June 1996 report on the housing initiative and reports from the Jeremiah officers for 1994-1996. Materials from 1993-1996 document the preparations to found and organize M.O.S.E.S.
  - Board Meetings 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Executive Board Meetings 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Board Meetings 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Board Meeting Materials 1997-1998 (Box 2)
  - Board Meeting Materials 1994-1996 (Box 2)
    (during formation of M.O.S.E.S.)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee 1993-1998 (Box 2)
    (includes material from Jeremiah before M.O.S.E.S.)
- M.O.S.E.S. Executive Board
  The M.O.S.E.S. Executive Board series spans from 1996-2000. There are executive board meeting minutes and materials, as well as committee reports, goals and evaluations of M.O.S.E.S., budget summaries, and calendars of events. It also includes 1997 M.O.S.E.S. meeting minutes, and 1996 meeting minutes for the joint boards and WDIFCO, during the discussion about if M.O.S.E.S. should be founded, and how it would work. Also of interest regarding the founding of M.O.S.E.S. are the records from the M.O.S.E.S. Visioning Conference on February 13, 1997 and the Gamaliel Foundation National Leadership Assembly in December 1997.
  - Executive Board Meetings 1999-2000 (Box 3)
  - Executive Board Meeting Materials 2000 (Box 3)
  - Executive Board, Joint Board, and WDIFCO 1996-1998 (Box 3)
    (includes material from predecessors of M.O.S.E.S.)
  - M.O.S.E.S. Executive Board Meeting materials 1997-1999 (Box 3)